Guide to the Nathaniel R. Howell Suffolk County, Nassau County, and Queens County deeds collection 1977.243
Brooklyn Historical Society
Nathaniel R. Howell Suffolk County, Nassau County, and Queens County deeds collection
1766-1934
Brooklyn Historical Society
Howell, Nathaniel R.
1977.243
2.5 Linear Feet in two manuscript boxes and one oversize box.
The Nathaniel R. Howell Suffolk County, Nassau County, and Queens County deeds collection spans the years 1766 to 1934. The collection consists primarily of Suffolk County, N.Y. land deeds. The bulk of the deeds are from the Suffolk County towns of East Hampton, Southampton, and Southold, N.Y., though the Suffolk County towns of Babylon, Brookhaven, Huntington, Islip, Riverhead, and Shelter Island are also represented in the collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Nathaniel R. Howell, 1956.
Arrangement
Materials have been grouped by county.
Historical note
Long Island is comprised of four counties: Suffolk County, Nassau County, Queens County, and Kings County. Suffolk, Queens, and Kings Counties, three of the original 12 counties of New York, were established by the British in 1683. Nassau County, established in 1899, is comprised of the eastern portion of land that was once part of Queens County. Today, the boroughs of Brooklyn and Queens, located on the western portion of Long Island, comprise the entirety of Kings County and Queens County, respectively. Suffolk County, occupying the eastern-most portion of Long Island, is by far the largest of the four counties by area and is known for its rich, fertile farmland and vast coastline.
Biographical note
Nathaniel R. Howell was from Long Island. He served as a councilor at the Long Island Historical Society (now the Center for Brooklyn History) from 1954-1956. He passed away in December 1956.
Other Finding Aids
This collection's accession file includes an index of family names, with their corresponding document numbers, for the early Suffolk County deeds located in Box 3. Please consult library staff for more information.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains land deeds and related documents from Nassau, Queens, and Suffolk counties between 1766 and 1934. The majority of the deeds are from Suffolk county, specifically the townships of East Hampton, Southampton, and Southold. It should be noted, however, that those townships included multiple villages which are now independent or incorporated into other townships. Deeds from Montauk and Amagansett are included in the folders for East Hampton; deeds from Quogue, Pondquogue, and Bridgehampton are included in the folders for Southampton; and deeds for Hogs Neck and Greenport are included in the folders for Southold. The related documents include correspondence, financial records, and court records; the majority of these relate to the transfer of land or its usage rights through marriage, death, or bankruptcy.
Legal documents; Real property -- New York (State) -- Suffolk County; Real property -- New York (State) -- Nassau County; Real property -- New York (State) -- Queens County; East Hampton (N.Y.); Huntington (N.Y.); Islip (N.Y.); Riverhead (N.Y.); Shelter Island (N.Y.); Queens County (N.Y.); Receipts (financial records); Indentures; Babylon (N.Y.); Brookhaven (N.Y.); Nassau County (N.Y.); Southold (N.Y.); Southampton (N.Y.); Suffolk County (N.Y.); Long Island (N.Y.); Deeds; Sag Harbor (N.Y.); Montauk (N.Y.); Quogue (N.Y.); Bridgehampton (N.Y.); Greenport (N.Y.); Dower; Salt industry and trade -- New York (State) -- Southold; Agreements; Hedges, Zephaniah; Hedges family; Edwards family
- Nassau County deeds, 1900-1909 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Queens County deeds and bonds, 1844-1911 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Suffolk County legal and financial documents, 1859-1900 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Babylon, Suffolk County, deeds, 1891-1931 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Brookhaven, Suffolk County, deeds and mortgages, 1808-1934 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- East Hampton, Suffolk County, court records, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- East Hampton, Suffolk County, deeds, 1803-1816 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- East Hampton, Suffolk County, deeds, 1817-1829 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- East Hampton, Suffolk County, deeds and correspondence, 1830-1870 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- East Hampton, Suffolk County, deeds and correspondence, 1890-1909 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Huntington, Suffolk County, deeds, 1800-1915 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Islip, Suffolk County, deeds, 1899-1930 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Railroad company documents, 1867-1876 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Riverhead, Suffolk County, Deeds and Mortgages, 1836-1934 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Sag Harbor, Suffolk County, deeds, 1824-1869 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Shelter Island, Suffolk County, deeds and mortgages, 1835-1945 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Southampton, Suffolk County, deeds, 1804-1839 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Southampton, Suffolk County, deeds and legal documents, 1840-1849 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Southampton, Suffolk County, deeds and legal documents, 1850-1869 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Southampton, Suffolk County, court records, 1869-1870 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Southampton, Suffolk County, court records, 1884-1888 (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
- Southampton, Suffolk County, deeds and legal documents, 1888-1926 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Southampton, Suffolk County, legal and financial documents, 1825-1904 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Southold, Suffolk County, deeds, 1810-1825 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Southold, Suffolk County, deeds, 1827-1914 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Southold, Suffolk County, legal documents, 1806-1894 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Joseph Crowell, Zephaniah Hedges, and Daniel L'Hommedieu business agreement, February 26, 1806; Crowell, Joseph; Hedges, Zephaniah; L'Hommedieu, Daniel (Box 3)
    Scope and Contents
    One business agreement between Joseph Crowell, Zephaniah Hedges, and Daniel L'Hommedieu, in which Crowell sells half his salt works to Hedges and L'Hommedieu. The salt works was located on Hog Neck within the town of Southold, Long Island. The document is dated February 26, 1806. Several typed transcriptions accompany the original document.
- Early Suffolk County deeds, 1766-1851; 1770-1790 (Box 3)
  According to this collection's accession file, Howell's original gift consisted of three "packets" of material. One of the packets consisted of "the earliest deeds in the total collection" and had been numbered by Howell from 1-41 (with number 37 omitted). This section of the collection, housed in an oversize box, maintains Howell's numerical order, which actually goes up to 42.
  Other Finding Aids
  An index of the names included in these documents, arranged in alphabetical order by surname and linked to the respective document(s) by their numbers, is included in the accession file and available to researchers upon request.